Hi everyone.
Today we are continuing our
implementation of makemore.
Now in the last lecture we implemented
the bigram language model and we
implemented both using counts and also
using a super simple neural network that
had a single linear layer.
Now this is the
Jupyter notebook that we built out last
lecture.
And we saw that the way we approached
this is that we looked at only the
single previous character and we
predicted the distribution for the
character that would go next in the
sequence. And we did that by taking
counts and normalizing them into
probabilities
so that each row here sums to one.
Now this is all well and good if you
only have one character of previous
context.
And this works and it's approachable.
The problem with this model of course is
that the predictions from this model are
not very good because you only take one
character of context. So the model
didn't produce very name-like sounding
things.
Now the problem with this approach
though is that if we are to take more
context into account when predicting the
next character in the sequence, things
quickly blow up and this table the size
of this table grows and in fact it grows
exponentially with the length of the
context.
Because if we only take a single
character at a time, that's 27
possibilities of context.
But if we take two characters in the
past and try to predict the third one,
suddenly the number of rows in this
matrix, you can look at it that way,
is 27 * 27. So there's 729 possibilities
for what could have come in the context.
If we take three characters as the
context, suddenly we have
20,000 possibilities of context.
And so that's just way too many rows of
this matrix. It's way too few counts
for each possibility and the whole thing
just kind of explodes and doesn't work
very well.
So that's why today we're going to move
on to this bullet point here and we're
going to implement a multi-layer
perceptron model to predict the next uh
in a sequence. And this modeling
approach that we're going to adopt
follows this paper Bengio et al. 2003.
So, I have the paper pulled up here.
Now, this isn't the very first paper
that proposed the use of uh multi-layer
perceptrons or neural networks to
predict the next character or token in a
sequence, but it's definitely one that
is uh was very influential around that
time. It is very often cited to stand in
for this idea, and I think it's a very
nice write-up. And so, this is the paper
that we're going to first look at and
then implement. Now, this paper has 19
pages. So, we don't have time to go into
the full detail of this paper, but I
invite you to read it. Uh it's very
readable, interesting, and has a lot of
interesting ideas in it as well.
In the introduction, they describe the
exact same problem I just described. And
then to address it, they propose the
following model.
Now, keep in mind that we are building a
character-level language model. So,
we're working on the level of
characters. In this paper, they have a
vocabulary of 17,000 possible words, and
they instead built a word-level language
model. But, we're going to still stick
with the characters, but we'll take the
same modeling approach.
Now, what they do is basically they
propose to take every one of these
words, 17,000 words, and they're going
to associate to each word a say
30-dimensional feature vector.
So, every word is now embedded into a
30-dimensional space. You can think of
it that way. So, we have 17,000 points
or vectors in a 30-dimensional space,
and that's um you might imagine that's
very crowded. That's a lot of points for
a very small space.
Now,
in the beginning, these words are
initialized completely randomly. So,
they're spread out at random.
But, then we're going to tune these
embeddings of these words using back
propagation. So, during the course of
training of this neural network, these
points or vectors are going to basically
move around in this space. And you might
imagine that, for example, words that
have very similar meanings or that are
indeed synonyms of each other might end
up in a very similar part of the space.
And conversely, words that mean very
different things would go somewhere else
in the space.
Now, their modeling approach otherwise
is identical to ours. They are using a
multi-layer neural network to predict
the next word given the previous words.
And to train the neural network, they
are maximizing the log likelihood of the
training data, just like we did.
So, the modeling approach itself is
identical. Now, here they have a
concrete example of this intuition.
Why does it work?
Basically, suppose that for example, you
are trying to predict "A dog was running
in a blank."
Now, suppose that the exact phrase "A
dog was running in a" has never occurred
in the training data.
And here you are at uh sort of test time
later when the model is deployed
somewhere.
And it's trying to make a sentence, and
it's saying "A dog was running in a
blank."
And because it's never encountered this
exact phrase in the training set, you're
out of distribution, as we say. Like,
you don't have fundamentally any
reason to suspect um
what might come next.
But, this approach actually allows you
to get around that. Because maybe you
didn't see the exact phrase "A dog was
running in a something." But, maybe
you've seen similar phrases. Maybe
you've seen the phrase "The dog was
running in a blank."
And maybe your network has learned that
A and the are like frequently are
interchangeable with each other. And so,
maybe it took the embedding for A and
the embedding for the, and it actually
put them like nearby each other in the
space. And so, you can transfer
knowledge through that embedding, and
you can generalize in that way.
Similarly, the network could know that
cats and dogs are animals, and they
co-occur in lots of very similar
contexts. And so, even though you
haven't seen this exact phrase,
or if you haven't seen exactly walking
or running, you can through the
embedding space transfer knowledge, and
you can generalize to novel scenarios.
So, let's now scroll down to the diagram
of the neural network. Uh they have a
nice uh diagram here.
And in this example, we are taking three
previous words
and we are trying to predict the fourth
word
in the sequence.
Now, these three previous words, as I
mentioned, we have a vocabulary of
17,000
possible words.
So, every one of these
basically are the index of the incoming
word.
And because there are 17,000 words, this
is an integer between 0 and 16,999.
Now, there's also a lookup table that
they call C.
This lookup table is a matrix that is
17,000 by, say, 30.
And basically what we're doing here is
we're treating this as a lookup table.
And so, every index is plucking out a
row of this embedding matrix
so that each index is converted to the
30-dimensional vector that corresponds
to the embedding vector for that word.
So, here we have the input layer of 30
neurons for three words, making up 90
neurons in total.
And here they're saying that this matrix
C is shared across all the words. So,
we're always indexing into the same
matrix C over and over.
for each one of these words.
Next up is the hidden layer of this
neural network.
The size of this hidden neural layer of
this neural net is a hyper parameter.
So, we use the word hyper parameter when
it's kind of like a design choice up to
the designer of the neural net. And this
can be as large as you'd like or as
small as you'd like. So, for example,
the size could be 100.
And we are going to go over multiple
choices of the size of this hidden
layer, and we're going to evaluate how
well they work.
So, say there were 100 neurons here,
all of them would be fully connected to
the 90 words or 90 um
numbers that make up these three words.
So, this is a fully connected layer.
Then there's a tanh non-linearity.
And then there's this output layer. And
because there are 17,000 possible words
that could come next, this layer has
17,000 neurons, and all of them are
fully connected to all of these neurons
in the hidden layer.
So there's a lot of parameters here
because there's a lot of words. So most
computation is here. This is the
expensive layer.
Now there are 17,000 logits here. So on
top of there, we have the softmax layer,
which we've seen in our previous video
as well. So every one of these logits is
exponentiated, and then everything is
normalized to sum to one so that we have
a nice probability distribution for the
next word in the sequence.
Now of course during training, we
actually have the label. We have the
identity of the next word in the
sequence.
That word or its index is used to pluck
out the probability of that word,
and then we are maximizing the
probability of that word with respect to
the parameters of this neural net.
So the parameters are the weights and
biases of this output layer, the weights
and biases of this hidden layer, and the
embedding lookup table C. And all of
that is optimized using backpropagation.
And these dashed arrows, ignore those.
That represents a variation of a neural
net that we are not going to explore in
this video.
So that's the setup, and now let's
implement it.
Okay, so I started a brand new notebook
for this lecture.
We are importing PyTorch, and we are
importing Matplotlib so we can create
figures.
Then I am reading all the names into a
list of words like I did before, and I'm
showing the first eight right here.
Keep in mind that we have a 32,000 in
total. These are just the first eight.
And then here I'm building out the
vocabulary of characters and all the
mappings from the characters as strings
to integers and vice versa.
Now the first thing we want to do is we
want to compile the data set for the
neural network. And I had to rewrite
this code.
I'll show you in a second what it looks
like.
So this is the code that I created for
the data set creation. So let me first
run it and then I'll briefly explain how
this works.
So first we're going to define something
called block size. And this is basically
the context length of how many
characters do we take to predict the
next one. So here in this example we're
taking three characters to predict the
fourth one. So we have a block size of
three. That's the size of the block that
supports the prediction.
Then here I'm building out the X and Y.
The X are the input to the neural net
and the Y are the labels for each
example inside X.
Then I'm iterating over the first five
words. I'm doing first five just for
efficiency while we are developing all
the code. But then later we're going to
come here and erase this so that we use
the entire training set.
So here I'm printing the word Emma.
And here I'm basically showing the
examples that we can generate. The five
examples that we can generate out of the
single
serve word Emma.
So
when we are given the context of just
dot dot dot, the first character in a
sequence is E.
In this context, the label is M.
When the context is this, the label is
M.
And so forth.
And so the way I build this out is first
I start with a padded context of just
zero tokens.
Then I iterate over all the characters.
I get the character in the sequence and
I basically build out the array Y of
this current character and the array X
which stores the current running
context.
And then here see I print everything and
here I
crop the context and enter the new
character in the sequence. So this is
kind of like a rolling window of
context.
Now we can change the block size here to
for example four.
And in that case we would be predicting
the fifth character given the previous
four.
Or it can be five and then it would look
like this.
Or it can be say 10.
And then it would look something like
this. We're taking 10 characters to
predict the 11th one.
And we're always padding with dots.
So let me bring this back to three, just
so that uh we have what we have here in
the paper.
And finally, the data set right now
looks as follows.
From these five words, we have created a
data set of 32 examples.
And each input to the neural net is
three integers, and we have a label that
is also an integer, uh Y. So X looks
like this.
These are the individual examples.
And then Y are the labels.
So
given this,
let's now write the neural network that
takes these X's and predicts the Y's.
First, let's build the embedding uh look
up table C.
So we have 27 possible characters, and
we're going to embed them in a lower
dimensional space.
In the paper, they have 17,000 words,
and they embed them in uh spaces as
small dimensional as 30. So they cram
17,000 um
words into 30-dimensional space. In our
case, we have only 27 possible
characters, so let's cram them in
something as small as to start with, for
example, a two-dimensional space.
So this look up table will be random
numbers,
and we'll have 27 rows, and we'll have
two columns.
Right? So each 20 each one of 27
characters will have a two-dimensional
embedding.
So that's our matrix C of embeddings, in
the beginning initialized randomly.
Now, before we embed all of the integers
inside the input X using this look up
table C,
let me actually just try to embed a
single individual integer, like say
five.
Um so we get a sense of how this works.
Now, one way this works, of course, is
we can just take the C, and we can index
into row five.
And that gives us a vector, the fifth
row of C.
And um
this is one way to do it.
The other way that I presented in the
previous lecture is actually seemingly
different, but actually identical.
So, in the previous lecture, what we did
is we took these integers and we used
the one-hot encoding to first encode
them.
So, F.one_hot
we want to encode integer five
and we want to tell it that the number
of classes is 27. So, that's the
26-dimensional vector of all zeros
except the fifth bit is turned on.
Now, this actually doesn't work.
The reason is that
this input actually must be a
torch.tensor.
And I'm making some of these errors
intentionally just so you get to see
some errors and how to fix them.
Uh so, this must be a tensor not an int,
fairly straightforward to fix.
We get a one-hot vector. The fifth
dimension is one and the shape of this
is 27.
And now notice that, just as I briefly
alluded to in the previous video, if we
take this one-hot vector and we multiply
it by C
then
um
what would you expect?
Well, number one
first you'd expect an error
because um
expected scalar type long but found
float. So, a little bit confusing, but
the problem here is that one-hot, the
data type of it
is long. It's a 64-bit integer. But,
this is a float tensor and so PyTorch
doesn't know how to multiply an int with
a float and that's why we had to
explicitly cast this to a float so that
we can multiply.
Now, the output actually here
is identical.
And that it's identical because of the
way the matrix uh multiplication here
works. We have the one-hot um vector
multiplying columns of C and because of
all the zeros, they actually end up
masking out everything in C except for
the fifth row, which is plucked out.
And so we actually arrive at the same
result.
And that tells you that here we can
interpret this first piece here, this
embedding of the integer. We can either
think of it as the integer indexing into
a lookup table C.
But equivalently, we can also think of
this little piece here as a first layer
of this bigger neural net.
This layer here has neurons that have no
non-linearity, they're no tan h, they're
just linear neurons, and their weight
matrix is C.
And then we are encoding integers into
one-hot and feeding those into a neural
net. And this first layer basically
embeds them.
So those are two equivalent ways of
doing the same thing. We're just going
to index because it's much much faster,
and we're going to discard this
interpretation of one-hot inputs into
neural nets. And we're just going to
index integers and create and use
embedding tables. Now, embedding a
single integer like five is easy enough.
We can simply ask PyTorch to retrieve
the fifth row of C. Or the row index
five of C.
But how do we simultaneously embed all
of these 32 by three integers stored in
array X?
Luckily, PyTorch indexing is fairly
flexible and quite powerful. So it
doesn't just work to um
ask for a single element five like this.
You can actually index using lists. So
for example, we can get the rows five,
six, and seven, and this will just work
like this. We can index with a list.
It doesn't just have to be a list, it
can also be a actually a tensor of
integers.
And we can index with that.
So this is a integer tensor 567, and
this will just work as well.
In fact, we can also, for example,
repeat row seven and retrieve it
multiple times. And uh
that same index will just get embedded
multiple times here.
So here we are indexing with a
one-dimensional
tensor of integers. But, it turns out
that you can also index with
multi-dimensional tensors of integers.
Here, we have a two-dimensional in
tensor of integers. So, we can simply
just do C at X.
And this just works.
And the shape of this
is
32 by 3, which is the original shape.
And now, for every one of those 32 by 3
integers, we've retrieved the embedding
vector here.
So, basically, we have that as an
example.
The 13th or example, index 13,
um the second dimension is the integer
one as an example.
And so, here, if we do C of X, which
gives us that array, and then we index
into 13 by 2 of that array,
then we we get the embedding
here.
And you can verify that C at one,
which is the integer at that location,
is indeed equal to this.
You see they're equal.
So, basically, long story short, PyTorch
indexing is awesome. And to embed
simultaneously
all of the integers in X, we can simply
do C of X. And that is our embedding.
And that just works.
Now, let's construct this layer here,
the hidden layer.
So, we have that W1, as I'll call it,
are these weights, which we will
initialize randomly.
Now, the number of inputs to this layer
is going to be 3 * 2, right? Because we
have two-dimensional embeddings, and we
have three of them.
So, the number of inputs is six.
And the number of neurons in this layer
is a variable up to us. Let's use 100
neurons as an example.
And then, biases will be also
initialized randomly as an example.
And let's And we just need 100 of them.
Now, the problem with this is we can't
simply Normally, we would take the
input, in this case that's embedding,
and we'd like to multiply it with these
weights.
And then we would like to add the bias.
This is roughly what we want to do.
But the problem here is that these
embeddings are stacked up in the
dimensions of this input tensor.
So, this will not work, this matrix
multiplication, because this is a shape
32 by 3 by 2, and I can't multiply that
by 6 by 100.
So, somehow we need to concatenate these
inputs here together so that we can do
something along these lines, which
currently does not work.
So, how do we transform this 32 by 3 by
2 into a 32 by 6 so that we can actually
perform this uh multiplication over
here? I'd like to show you that there
are usually many ways of uh implementing
what you'd like to do in torch.
And some of them will be faster, better,
shorter, etc.
And that's because torch is a very large
library, and it's got lots and lots of
functions. So, if we just go to the
documentation and click on torch, you'll
see that my slider here is very tiny,
and that's because there are so many
functions that you can call on these
tensors
to transform them, create them, multiply
them, add them, perform all kinds of
different operations on them.
And so, this is kind of like
the space of possibility, if you will.
Now, one of the things that you can do
is if we can control here, control F for
concatenate. And we see that there's a
function, torch.cat, short for
concatenate.
And this concatenates a given sequence
of tensors in a given dimension.
And uh these tensors must have the same
shape, etc. So, we can use the
concatenate operation to, in a naive
way, concatenate these three embeddings
for each input.
So, in this case, we have emb of
emb of the shape. And really what we
want to do is we want to retrieve these
three parts and concatenate them.
So, we want to grab all the examples.
We want to grab
first the zeroth um
index and then all of
this.
So, this plucks out
the 32 by 2 embeddings of just the first
word here.
And so, basically we want this guy.
We want the first dimension. And we want
the second dimension.
And these are the three pieces
individually.
And then we want to treat this as a
sequence and we want to torch.cat
on that sequence. So, this is the list.
torch.cat takes a sequence of tensors.
And then we have to tell it along which
dimension to concatenate.
So, in this case all these are 32 by 2
and we want to concatenate not across
dimension zero, but across dimension
one.
So, passing in one
gives us a result.
The shape of this is 32 by 6 exactly as
we'd like.
So, that basically took 32 and squashed
these by concatenating them into 32 by
6.
Now, this is kind of ugly because this
code would not generalize if we want to
later change the block size. Right now,
we have three inputs.
Three words. But what if we had five?
Then here we would have to change the
code because I'm indexing directly.
Well, torch comes to rescue again
because there turns out to be a function
called unbind.
And it removes a tensor dimension.
So, removes a tensor dimension, returns
a tuple of all slices along a given
dimension without it.
So, this is exactly what we need.
And basically when we call torch.unbind
torch.unbind
of emb and passing dimension um one,
index one.
This gives us a list of
um a list of tensors exactly equivalent
to this.
So, running this
gives us a length
three
and it's exactly this list. And so, we
can call torch.cat on it.
And along the first dimension.
And this works.
And the shape is the same.
But now this is uh it doesn't matter if
we have block size three or five or 10,
this will just work.
So, this is one way to do it. But it
turns out that in this case, there's
actually a significantly better and more
efficient way. And this gives me an
opportunity to hint at some of the
internals of torch.tensor.
So, let's create
an array here
of elements from zero to 17. And the
shape of this
is just 18. It's a single vector of 18
numbers.
It turns out that we can very quickly
re-represent this as different sized and
dimensional tensors.
We do this by calling a view.
And we can say that actually this is not
a single vector of 18, this is a 2x9
tensor.
Or alternatively, this is a 9x2 tensor.
Or this is actually a 3x3x2 tensor.
As long as the total number of elements
here multiply to be the same, uh this
will just work.
And in PyTorch, this operation calling
dot view is extremely efficient.
And the reason for that is that in each
tensor, there's something called the
underlying storage.
And the storage is just the numbers
always as a one-dimensional vector. And
this is how this tensor is represented
in the computer memory. It's always a
one-dimensional vector.
But when we call that view, we are
manipulating some of attributes of that
tensor that dictate how this
one-dimensional sequence is interpreted
to be an N-dimensional tensor.
And so, what's happening here is that no
memory is being changed, copied, moved,
or created when we call dot view. The
The storage
is identical, but when you call dot
view, some of the internal um
attributes of the view of this tensor
are being manipulated and changed. In
particular, there's something There's
something called a storage offset,
strides, and shapes, and those are
manipulated so that this one-dimensional
sequence of bytes is seen as different
n-dimensional arrays.
There's a blog post here from Eric
called PyTorch Internals, where he goes
into some of this with respect to tensor
and how the view of a tensor is
represented.
And this is really just like a logical
construct of representing the physical
memory.
And uh so this is a pretty good um
blog post that you can go into. I might
also create an entire video on the
internals of torch tensor and how this
works.
For here, we just note that this is an
extremely efficient operation.
And if I delete this and come back to
our emb,
we see that the shape of our emb is 32
by 3 by 2, but we can simply ask for
PyTorch to view this instead as a 32 by
6.
And the way this gets flattened into a
32 by 6 array
just happens that
these two
get stacked up in a single row. And so
that's basically the concatenation
operation that we're after.
And you can verify that this actually
gives the exact same result as what we
had before.
So this is an element-wise equals, and
you can see that all the elements of
these two tensors are the same.
And so we get the exact same result.
So long story short, we can actually
just come here,
and if we just view this as a 32 by 6
um instead, then this multiplication
will work and give us the hidden states
that we're after.
So if this is H,
then H.shape is now the 100-dimensional
activations for every one of our 32
examples.
And this gives the desired result. Let
me do two things here. Number one, let's
not use 32. We can, for example, do
something like
um
emb.shape
at zero.
So that we don't hardcode these numbers.
And this would work for any size of this
emb.
Or alternatively, we can also do -1.
When we do -1, PyTorch will infer what
this should be.
Because the number of elements must be
the same, and we're saying that this is
six, PyTorch will derive that this must
be 32 or whatever else it is if emb is
of different size.
The other thing is here,
um
one more thing I'd like to point out is
here when we do the concatenation,
this actually is much less efficient
because um this concatenation would
create a whole new tensor with a whole
new storage. So new memory is being
created because there's no way to
concatenate tensors just by manipulating
the view attributes. So this is
inefficient and creates all kinds of new
memory.
Uh so let me delete this now.
We don't need this.
And here to calculate H, we want to also
dot tanh
of this to get our
oops, to get our H.
So these are now numbers between -1 and
1 because of the tanh.
And we have that the shape is 32 by 100.
And that is basically this hidden layer
of activations here
for every one of our 32 examples.
Now there's one more thing I glossed
over that we have to be very careful
with, and that's this and that's this
plus here.
In particular, we want to make sure that
the broadcasting will do what we like.
The shape of this is 32 by 100, and B1's
shape is 100.
So we see that the addition here will
broadcast these two. And in particular,
we have 32 by 100 broadcasting to 100.
So broadcasting will align on the right,
create a fake dimension here.
So, this will become a 1 by 100 row
vector.
And then it will copy vertically
for every one of these rows of 32 and do
an element-wise addition.
So, in this case, the correct thing will
be happening because the same bias
vector
will be added to all the rows
of
this matrix.
So, that is correct. That's what we'd
like. And uh it's always good practice
to just make sure uh so that you don't
shoot yourself in the foot. And finally,
let's create the final layer here.
So, let's create
W2 and B2.
The input now is 100.
And the output number of neurons will be
for us 27 because we have 27 possible
characters that come next.
So, the biases will be 27 as well.
So, therefore, the logits, which are the
outputs of this neural net,
are going to be um
H multiplied by W2 plus B2.
Logits.shape is 32 by 27.
And the logits look
good. Now, exactly as we saw in the
previous video, we want to take these
logits and we want to first exponentiate
them to get our fake counts.
And then we want to normalize them into
a probability.
So, prob is counts.divide.
And now uh counts.sum
along the first dimension and keep dims
as true, exactly as in the previous
video.
And so,
prob.shape now is 32 by 27.
And you'll see that every row of prob
sums to one, so it's normalized.
So, that gives us the probabilities.
Now, of course, we have the actual
letter that comes next. And that comes
from this array Y,
which we which we created during the
data set creation. So, Y is this last
piece here, which is the identity of the
next character in the sequence that we'd
like to now predict.
So, what we'd like to do now is just as
in the previous video, we'd like to
index into the rows of prob, and each
row we'd like to pluck out the
probability assigned to the correct
character
as given here.
So, first we have torch.arange of 32,
which is kind of like a iterator over um
numbers from 0 to 31,
and then we can index into prob in the
following way.
prob in torch.arange of 32, which
iterates the rows. And then in each row,
we'd like to grab this column as given
by Y.
So, this gives the current probabilities
as assigned by this neural network with
this setting of its weights
to the correct character in the
sequence.
And you can see here that this looks
okay for some of these characters. Like
this is basically 0.2,
but it doesn't look very good at all for
many other characters. Like this is
0.0701
probability. And so, the network thinks
that some of these are extremely
unlikely. But of course, we haven't
trained the neural network yet. So,
um this will improve, and ideally all of
these numbers here of course are one
because then we are correctly predicting
the next character.
Now, just as in the previous video, we
want to take these probabilities, we
want to look at the log probability, and
then we want to look at the average log
probability,
and then negative of it to create the
negative log likelihood loss.
So, the loss here is 17.
And this is the loss that we'd like to
minimize to get the network to predict
the correct character in the sequence.
Okay, so I rewrote everything here and
made it a bit more respectable.
So, here's our data set.
Here's all the parameters that we
defined.
I'm now using a generator to make it
reproducible.
I clustered all the parameters into a
single list of parameters, so that for
example, it's easy to count them and see
that in total we currently have about
3,400 parameters.
And this is the forward pass as we
developed it.
And we arrive at a single number here,
the loss, that is currently expressing
how well this neural network works with
the current setting of parameters.
Now, I would like to make it even more
respectable.
So, in particular, see these lines here,
where we take the logits and we
calculate the loss.
Um we're not actually reinventing the
wheel here. This is just um
classification, and many people use
classification, and that's why there is
a functional.cross_entropy function in
PyTorch to calculate this much more
efficiently.
So, we could just simply call
f.cross_entropy,
and we can pass in the logits, and we
can pass in the
uh array of targets, Y.
And this calculates the exact same loss.
Um so, in fact, we can simply put this
here
and erase these three lines, and we're
going to get the exact same result. Now,
there are actually many good reasons to
prefer f.cross_entropy over rolling your
own implementation like this. I did this
for educational reasons, but you'd never
use this in practice. Why is that?
Number one, when you use
f.cross_entropy, PyTorch will not
actually create all these intermediate
tensors, because these are all new
tensors in memory, and all this is
fairly inefficient to run like this.
Instead, PyTorch will cluster up all
these operations and very often create
have a fused kernels that very
efficiently evaluate these expressions
that are sort of like clustered uh
mathematical operations.
Number two, the backward pass can be
made much more efficient. And not just
because it's a fused kernel, but also
analytically and mathematically, it's
much it's often a very much uh simpler
backward pass to implement.
We actually saw this with micrograd.
You see here when we implemented tanh,
the forward pass of this operation to
calculate the tanh was actually a fairly
complicated mathematical expression.
But because it's a clustered
mathematical expression, when we did the
backward pass, we didn't individually
backward through the exp and the two
times and the minus one and the
division, etc. We just said it's 1 - t
squared. And that's a much simpler
mathematical expression.
And we were able to do this because
we're able to reuse calculations and
because we are able to mathematically
and analytically derive the derivative
and often that expression simplifies
mathematically. And so there's much less
to implement.
So not only can can it be made more
efficient because it runs in a fused
kernel, but also because the expressions
can take a much simpler form
mathematically.
So that's number one. Number two,
under the hood, after cross entropy can
also be significantly more
um
numerically well-behaved. Let me show
you an example of how this works.
Suppose we have a logits of -2, 3, -3,
0, and 5.
And then we are taking the exponent of
it and normalizing it to sum to one. So
when logits take on these values,
everything is well and good and we get a
nice probability distribution.
Now consider what happens when some of
these logits take on more extreme values
and that can happen during optimization
of a neural network.
Suppose that some of these numbers grow
very negative, like say -100.
Then actually everything will come out
fine. We still get the probabilities
that um you know, are well-behaved and
they sum to one and everything is great.
But because of the way the exp works, if
you have very positive logits, like say
positive 100 in here,
you actually start to run into trouble
and we get not a number here.
And the reason for that is that these
counts
have an inf here.
So if you pass in a very negative number
to exp, you just get a very negative
Sorry, not negative, but very small
number, very very near zero and that's
fine.
But if you pass in a very positive
number, suddenly we run out of range in
our floating point number that
represents these counts.
So basically we're taking E and we're
raising it to the power of 100 and that
gives us inf because we run out of
dynamic range on this floating point
number that is count.
And so, we cannot pass very large logits
through this expression.
Now, let me reset these numbers to
something reasonable.
The way PyTorch solves this is that you
see how we have a well-behaved result
here.
It turns out that because of the
normalization here, you can actually
offset logits by any arbitrary constant
value that you want. So, if I add one
here,
you actually get the exact same result.
Or if I add two,
or if I subtract three.
Any offset will produce the exact same
probabilities.
So, because negative numbers are okay,
but positive numbers can actually
overflow this exp, what PyTorch does is
it internally calculates the maximum
value that occurs in the logits and it
subtracts it. So, in this case it would
subtract five.
And so, therefore the greatest number in
logits will become zero and all the
other numbers will become some negative
numbers.
And then the result of this is always
well-behaved. So, even if we have a 100
here previously,
not good, but because PyTorch will
subtract 100, this will work.
And so, there's many good reasons to
call cross entropy. Number one, the
forward pass can be much more efficient.
The backward pass can be much more
efficient. And also things can be much
more numerically well-behaved. Okay, so
let's now set up the training of this
neural net.
We have the forward pass.
Uh we don't need these. Except we have
the loss is equal to the after cross
entropy. That's the forward pass.
Then we need the backward pass. First we
want to set the gradients to be zero.
So, for P and parameters, we want to
make sure that P.grad is none, which is
the same as setting it to zero in
PyTorch.
And then loss.backward to populate those
gradients.
Once we have the gradients, we can do
the parameter update. So, for P in
parameters, we want to take all the data
and we want to nudge it
learning rate times p.grad.
And then we want to repeat this
a few times.
Um
And let's print the loss here as well.
Now, this won't suffice and will create
an error because we also have to go for
P in parameters
and we have to make sure that
p.requires_grad
is set to true in PyTorch.
And this should just work.
Okay. So, we started off with loss of 17
and we're decreasing it.
Let's run longer.
And you see how the loss decreases
a lot here. So,
if we just run for 1,000 times, we get a
very, very low loss. And that means that
we're making very good predictions. Now,
the reason that this is so
straightforward right now is because
we're only um
overfitting 32 examples.
So, we only have 32 examples uh of the
first five words
and therefore it's very easy to make
this neural net fit only these two 32
examples because we have 3,400
parameters and only 32 examples. So,
we're doing what's called overfitting a
single batch of the data
and getting a very low loss and good
predictions. Um but that's just because
we have so many parameters for so few
examples. So, it's easy to uh make this
be very low.
Now, we're not able to achieve exactly
zero. And the reason for that is we can,
for example, look at the logits which
are being predicted.
And uh we can look at the max along the
first dimension.
And in PyTorch, uh max reports both the
actual values that take on the maximum
uh, number, but also the indices of
these.
And you'll see that the indices are very
close to the labels.
But in some cases they differ. For
example, in this very first example, uh,
the predicted index is 19, but the label
is five.
And we're not able to make loss be zero,
and fundamentally that's because here
the very first or the zeroth index is
the example where dot dot dot is
supposed to predict E. But you see how
dot dot dot is also supposed to predict
an O. And dot dot dot is also supposed
to predict an I, and then S as well. And
so basically E, O, A, or S are all
possible outcomes in the training set
for the exact same input. So we're not
able to completely overfit and um,
and make the loss be exactly zero. Uh,
so but we're getting very close in the
cases where uh, there's a unique input
for a unique output. In those cases we
do what's called overfit, and we
basically get the exact same and the
exact correct result.
So now all we have to do
is we just need to make sure that we
read in the full data set and optimize
the neural net.
Okay, so let's swing back up where we
created the data set.
And we see that here we only use the
first five words. So let me now erase
this,
and let me erase the print statements,
otherwise we'll be printing way too
much.
And so when we process the full data set
of all the words, we now have 228,000
examples instead of just 32.
So let's now scroll back down. The
dataset is much larger. We initialize
the weights, the same number of
parameters. They all require gradients.
And then let's push this print out loss
dot item to be here.
And let's just see how the optimization
goes if we run this.
Okay, so we started with a fairly high
loss, and then as we're optimizing, the
loss is coming down.
But you'll notice that it takes quite a
bit of time for every single iteration.
So, let's actually address that. Because
we're doing way too much work forwarding
and backwarding 220,000 examples.
In practice, what people usually do is
they perform forward and backward pass
and update on mini batches of the data.
So, what we will want to do is we want
to randomly select some portion of the
data set, and that's a mini batch, and
then only forward backward and update on
that little mini batch. And then, um,
we iterate on those mini batches.
So, in PyTorch, we can, for example, use
torch.randint.
We can generate numbers between 0 and 5
and make 32 of them.
Um,
I believe the size has to be a tuple
in PyTorch.
So, we can have a tuple 32 of numbers
between 0 and 5. But, actually, we want
x.shape of 0 here.
And so, this creates uh integers that
index into our data set, and there's 32
of them.
So, if our mini batch size is 32, then
we can come here and we can first do uh
mini batch
construct.
So, in the integers that we want to
optimize in this
um single iteration are in the ix.
And then, we want to index into x with
ix to only grab those rows.
So, we're only getting 32 rows of x.
And therefore, embeddings will again be
32 by 3 by 2, not 200,000 by 3 by 2.
And then, this ix has to be used not
just to index into x, but also to index
into y.
And now, this should be mini batches,
and this should be much much faster. So,
Okay, so it's instant almost.
So, this way, we can run many many
examples
nearly instantly and decrease the loss
much much faster.
Now, because we're only dealing with
mini batches, the quality of our
gradient is lower. So, the direction is
not as reliable. It's not the actual
gradient direction.
But, the gradient direction is good
enough even when it's estimating on only
32 examples that it is useful.
And so, it's much better to have an
approximate gradient and just make more
steps than it is to evaluate the exact
gradient and take fewer steps. So,
that's why in practice,
uh this works quite well.
So, let's continue the optimization.
Let me take out this loss.item from here
and uh place it over here at the end.
Okay, so we're hovering around 2.5 or
so.
Um
however, this is only the loss for that
mini batch. So, let's actually evaluate
the loss
here
for all of X
and for all of Y, just so we have a full
sense of exactly how well the model is
doing right now.
So, right now we're at about 2.7 on the
entire training set.
So, let's run the optimization for a
while.
Okay, we're at 2.6.
2.57
2.53
Okay.
So, one issue, of course, is we don't
know if we're stepping too slow or too
fast.
Um so, this point one, I just guessed
it. So, one question is, how do you
determine this learning rate?
And um how do we gain confidence that
we're stepping in the right um
sort of speed? So, I'll show you one way
to determine a reasonable learning rate.
It works as follows. Let's reset our
parameters
to the initial
um
settings.
And now, let's
print in every step.
But, let's only do 10 steps or so.
Or maybe maybe 100 steps.
We want to find like a very reasonable
set
search range, if you will. So, for
example, if this is like very low,
then
we see that the loss is barely
decreasing. So, that's not
That's like too low, basically. So,
let's try
this one.
Okay, so we're decreasing the loss, but
like not very quickly. So, that's a
pretty good low range.
Now, let's reset it again.
And now, let's try to find the place at
which the loss kind of explodes.
Uh so, maybe at -1.
Okay, we see that we're minimizing the
loss, but you see how it's kind of
unstable. It goes up and down quite a
bit.
Um so, -1 is probably like a fast
learning rate. Let's try -10.
Okay, so this isn't optimizing. This is
not working very well. So, -10 is way
too big. -1 was already kind of big. Um
so, therefore, -1 was like somewhat
reasonable if I reset.
So, I'm thinking that the right learning
rate is somewhere between
um -0.001
and um
-1.
So, the way we can do this here is we
can use uh torch.linspace.
And we want to basically do something
like this, between 0 and 1, but
um
uh number of steps is one more parameter
that's required. Let's do 1,000 steps.
This creates 1,000
um numbers between 0.001 and 1.
But, it doesn't really make sense to
step between these linearly. So,
instead, let me create learning rate
exponent.
And instead of 0.001, this will be a -3,
and this will be a 0. And then, the
actual uh LRs that we want to search
over are going to be 10 to the power of
LRE.
So, now what we're doing is we're
stepping linearly between the exponents
of these learning rates. This is 0.001,
and this is 1, because uh 10 to the
power of zero is one.
And therefore, we are spaced
exponentially in this interval.
So, these are the candidate learning
rates
that we want to sort of like search
over, roughly.
So, now what we're going to do is
here, we are going to run the
optimization for 1,000 steps.
And instead of using a fixed number, we
are going to use learning rate
indexing into here, lrs of I, and make
this I.
So, basically, let me reset this to be,
again, starting from random,
creating these learning rates between
negative um 0.0 between 0.001 and um
one, but exponentially stepped.
And here what we're doing is we're
iterating a thousand times. We're going
to use the learning rate
um that's in the beginning very, very
low. In the beginning, it's going to be
0.001, but by the end, it's going to be
one.
And then we're going to step with that
learning rate.
And now what we want to do is we want to
keep track of the uh um
learning rates that we used, and we want
to look at the losses that resulted.
And so here, let me
track stats.
So, lri.append lr,
and um
loss i.append
loss.item.
Okay.
So, again, reset everything,
and then run.
And so, basically, we started with a
very low learning rate, and we went all
the way up to uh learning rate of
negative one. And now what we can do is
we can plt.plot,
and we can plot the two. So, we can plot
the learning rates on the x-axis, and
the losses we saw on the y-axis.
And often, you're going to find that
your plot looks something like this,
where in the beginning, um
you had very low learning rates. We
basically anything
barely anything happened.
Then we got to like a nice spot here.
And then as we increase the learning
rate enough, uh, we basically started to
be kind of unstable here.
So a good learning rate turns out to be
somewhere around here.
Um, and because we have LRI here,
um,
we actually may want to, um,
do not LR, uh,
not the learning rate, but the exponent.
So that would be the LRE at I is maybe
what we want to log. So let me reset
this and redo that calculation.
But now on the x-axis we have the, um,
exponent of the learning rate. And so we
can see the exponent of the learning
rate that is good to use. It would be
sort of like roughly in the valley here,
because here the learning rates are just
way too low. And then here where we
expect relatively good learning rate
somewhere here. And then here things are
starting to explode. So somewhere around
-1 as the exponent of the learning rate
is a pretty good setting. And 10 to the
-1 is .1. So .1 is actually .1 was
actually a fairly good learning rate
around here.
And that's what we had in the initial
setting.
Um, but that's roughly how you would
determine it.
And so here now we can take out the
tracking of these.
And we can just simply set LR to be 10
to the -1 or
basically otherwise .1 as it was before.
And now we have some confidence that
this is actually a fairly good learning
rate.
And so now we can do is we can crank up
the iterations.
We can reset our optimization.
And, um,
we can run for a pretty long time using
this learning rate.
Oops, and we don't want to print. That's
way too much printing.
So let me again reset.
And run 10,000 steps.
Okay, so we're at 0.2 2.48 roughly.
Let's run another 10,000 steps.
2.46
And now let's do one learning rate
decay. What this means is we're going to
take our learning rate and we're going
to 10x lower it. And so we're at the
late stages of training potentially and
we may want to go uh a bit slower.
Let's do one more actually at 0.1 just
to see if
we're making a dent here.
Okay, we're still making dent. And by
the way, the bigram loss that we
achieved last video was 2.45. So we've
already surpassed the bigram model.
And once I get a sense that this is
actually kind of starting to plateau
off, uh people like to do as I mentioned
this learning rate decay. So let's try
to decay the loss,
uh the learning rate I mean.
And we achieve at about 2.3 now.
Obviously, this is janky and not exactly
how you would train it in production,
but this is roughly what you're going
through. You first find a decent
learning rate using the approach that I
showed you.
Then you start with that learning rate
and you train for a while.
And then at the end people like to do a
learning rate decay where you decay the
learning rate by say a factor of 10 and
you do a few more steps and then you get
a trained network, roughly speaking.
So we've achieved 2.3 and uh
dramatically improved on the bigram
language model using this simple neural
net as described here
um using these 3,400 parameters.
Now there's something we have to be
careful with.
I said that we have a better model
because we are achieving a lower loss,
2.3, much lower than 2.45 with the
bigram model previously.
Now that's not exactly true. And the
reason that's not true is that
this is actually fairly small model, but
these models can get larger and larger
if you keep adding neurons and
parameters. So, you can imagine that we
don't potentially have a thousand
parameters. We could have 10,000 or
100,000 or millions of parameters.
And as the capacity of the neural
network grows,
it becomes more and more capable of
overfitting your training set.
What that means is that the loss on the
training set, on the data that you're
training on, will become very, very low,
as low as zero.
But all that the model is doing is
memorizing your training set verbatim.
So, if you take that model, and it looks
like it's working really well, but you
try to sample from it, you will
basically only get examples exactly as
they are in the training set. You won't
get any new data.
In addition to that, if you try to
evaluate the loss on some withheld names
or other words, you will actually see
that the loss on those can be very high.
As a basically, it's not a good model.
So, the standard in the field it is is
to split up your data set into three
splits, as we call them. We have the
training split, the dev split or the
validation split,
and the test split.
So, training split,
test or um sorry, dev or validation
split,
and test split.
And typically, this would be say 80% of
your data set, this could be 10% and
this 10% roughly.
So, you have these three splits of the
data.
Now, these 80% of your training of of
the data set, the training set, is used
to optimize the parameters of the model,
just like we're doing here, using
gradient descent.
These 10% of the um examples, the dev or
validation split, they're used for
development over all the hyper
parameters of your model. So, hyper
parameters are for example, the size of
this hidden layer,
the size of the embedding. So, this is a
hundred or a two for us, but we could
try different things.
The strength of the regularization,
which we aren't using yet so far.
So, there's lots of different hyper
parameters and settings that go into
defining a neural net, and you can try
many different variations of them and
see whichever one works best on your
validation split.
So, this is used to train the
parameters.
This is used to train the hyper
And test split is used to evaluate uh
basically the performance of the model
at the end.
So, we're only evaluating the loss on
the test split very, very sparingly and
very few times because every single time
you evaluate your test loss and you
learn something from it,
you are basically starting to also train
on the test split. So, you are only
allowed to test the loss on the test set
um very, very few times. Otherwise, you
risk overfitting to it as well as you
experiment on your model.
So, let's also split up our training
data into train, dev, and test. And
then, we are going to train on train and
only evaluate on test very, very
sparingly.
Okay, so here we go.
Here is where we took all the words and
put them into X and Y tensors.
So, instead, let me create a new cell
here and let me just copy-paste some
code here
because I don't think it's that
complex, but um
we're going to try to save a little bit
of time.
I'm converting this to be a function
now. And this function takes some list
of words and builds the arrays X and Y
for those words only.
And then here, I am shuffling up all the
words. So, these are the input words
that we get.
We are randomly shuffling them all up.
And then, um
we're going to
set N1 to be
the number of examples, that's 80% of
the words, and N2 to be 90% of the
weight of the words.
So, basically, if length of words is
30,000, N1 is
Oh, sorry. I should probably run this.
N1 is 25,000 and N2 is 28,000.
And so, here we see that I'm calling
build data set to build the training set
X and Y
by indexing into up to N1. So, we're
going to have only 25,000 training
words.
And then we're going to have um
roughly
N2 minus N1
3,000 validation examples or dev
examples. And we're going to have
um
len of words basically minus N2
or 3,204
examples
here for the test set.
So,
now we have X's and Y's for all those
three splits.
Um
Oh, yeah. I'm printing their size here
inside the function as well.
But here we don't have words, but these
are already the individual examples made
from those words.
So, let's now scroll down here.
And the data set now for training is
more like this.
And then when we reset the network,
when we're training, we're only going to
be training using X train,
X train, and Y train.
So, that's the only thing we're training
on.
Let's see where we are on the
single batch.
Let's now train maybe a few more steps.
Training a neural network can take a
while. Usually, you don't do it in line.
You launch a bunch of jobs and you wait
for them to finish.
Um
can take in multiple days and so on.
Luckily, this is a very small network.
Okay, so the loss is pretty good. Oh, we
accidentally used a learning rate that
is way too low.
So, let me actually come back.
We use the decay learning rate of 0.01.
So, this will train much faster.
And then here, when we evaluate, uh
let's use the dev set here.
X dev
and Y dev to evaluate the loss.
Okay.
Uh
and let's not decay the learning rate
and only do say 10,000 examples.
And let's evaluate the dev loss once
here.
Okay, so we're getting about 2.3 on dev.
And so, the neural network when it was
training did not see these dev examples.
It hasn't optimized on them. And yet,
when we evaluate the loss on these dev,
we actually get a pretty decent loss.
And so, we can also look at what the
loss is on all of training set.
Oops.
And so, we see that the training and the
dev loss are about equal. So, we're not
over- fitting. Um this model is not
powerful enough to just be purely
memorizing the data. And so far, we are
what's called under-fitting because the
training loss and the dev or test losses
are roughly equal. So, what that
typically means is that our network is
very tiny, very small. And we expect to
make uh performance improvements by
scaling up the size of this neural net.
So, let's do that now. So, let's come
over here
and let's increase the size of the
neural net.
The easiest way to do this is we can
come here to the hidden layer, which
currently has 100 neurons, and let's
just pump this up. So, let's do 300
neurons.
And then, this is also 300 biases. And
here we have 300 inputs into the final
layer.
So,
let's initialize our neural net. We now
have 10,000 10,000 parameters instead of
3,000 parameters.
And then, we're not using this.
And then here, what I'd like to do is
I'd like to actually uh keep track of uh
that
um
Okay, let's just do this. Let's keep
stats again.
And here when we're keeping track of the
loss, let's just also keep track of the
steps. And let's just have a eye here.
And let's train on 30,000.
Or rather say
Okay, let's try 30,000.
And we are at 0.1.
And
we should be able to run this.
And optimize neural net.
And then here basically I want to
PLT.plot
the steps
against the loss.
So these are the x's and y's.
And this is
the loss function and how it's being
optimized.
Now you see that there's quite a bit of
thickness to this, and that's because we
are optimizing over these mini batches.
And the mini batches create a little bit
of noise in this.
Uh where are we in the dev set? We are
at 2.5. So we still haven't optimized
this neural net very well.
And that's probably because we made it
bigger. It might take longer for this
neural net to converge.
Um
and so let's continue training.
yeah, let's just continue training.
One possibility is that the batch size
is so low
that we just have way too much noise in
the training. And we may want to
increase the batch size so that we have
a bit more
correct gradient and we're not thrashing
too much. And we can actually like
optimize more properly.
Okay.
Uh this will now become meaningless
because we've reinitialized these. So
yeah, this looks not pleasing like now.
But there probably is like a tiny
improvement, but it's so hard to tell.
Uh let's go again.
2.52
Let's try to decrease the learning rate
by a factor of two.
Okay, we're at 2.32.
Let's continue training.
We basically expect to see a lower loss
than what we had before, because now we
have a much, much bigger model, and we
were underfitting. So, we'd expect that
increasing the size of the model should
help the neural net.
2.32 Okay, so that's not happening too
well.
Now, one other concern is that even
though we've made the tanh layer here,
uh the hidden layer, much, much bigger,
it could be that the bottleneck of the
network right now are these embeddings
that are two dimensional. It can be that
we're just cramming way too many
characters into just two dimensions, and
the neural net is not able to really use
that space effectively, and that that is
sort of like the bottleneck to our
network's performance.
Okay, 2.23. So, just by decreasing the
learning rate, I was able to make quite
a bit of progress. Let's run this one
more time.
And then evaluate the training and the
dev loss.
Now, one more thing after training that
I'd like to do is I'd like to visualize
the um
embedding vectors for these um
characters before we scale up uh the
embedding size from two.
Because we'd like to make uh this
bottleneck potentially go away.
But once I make this greater than two,
we won't be able to visualize them.
So here, okay, we're at 2.23 and 2.24.
So um
we're not improving much more, and maybe
the bottleneck now is the character
embedding size, which is two.
So here I have a bunch of code that will
create a figure,
and then we're going to visualize
the embeddings that were trained by the
neural net
on these characters. Because right now
the embedding size is just two, so we
can visualize all the characters with
the X and the Y coordinates as the two
embedding locations for each of these
characters.
And so here are the X coordinates and
the Y coordinates, which are the columns
of C.
And then for each one, I also include
the text of the little character.
So here what we see is actually kind of
interesting.
Um
the network has basically learned to
separate out the characters and cluster
them a little bit. Uh so for example,
you see how the vowels
a e i o u are clustered up here.
So what that's telling us that is that
the neural net treats these as very
similar, right? Because when they feed
into the neural net, the embedding
uh for all of these characters is very
similar. And so the neural net thinks
that they're very similar and kind of
like interchangeable, if that makes
sense.
Um
then the the points that are like really
far away are for example Q. Q is kind of
treated as an exception, and Q has a
very special embedding vector, so to
speak.
Similarly, dot, which is a special
character, is all the way out here.
And a lot of the other letters are sort
of like clustered up here.
And so it's kind of interesting that
there's a little bit of structure here
um after the training,
and it's not definitely not random, and
these embeddings make sense.
So we're now going to scale up the
embedding size and won't be able to
visualize it directly, but we expect
that because we're underfitting,
and we made this layer much bigger and
did not sufficiently improve the loss.
We're thinking that the
um
constraint to better performance right
now could be these embedding vectors.
So, let's make them bigger. Okay, so
let's scroll up here.
And now we don't have two-dimensional
embeddings, we are going to have
say 10-dimensional embeddings for each
word.
Then
this layer will receive 3 * 10, so 30
inputs
will go into
um
the hidden layer.
Let's also make the hidden layer a bit
smaller. So, instead of 300, let's just
do 200 neurons in that hidden layer.
So, now the total number of elements
will be slightly bigger at 11,000.
And then we here we have to be a bit
careful because um
okay, the learning rate we set to 0.1.
Here we are hardcoding six and
obviously, if you're working in
production, you don't want to be
hardcoding magic numbers. But instead of
six, this should now be 30.
Um
and let's run it for 50,000 iterations
and let me split out the initialization
here outside
so that when we run this cell multiple
times, it's not going to wipe out our
loss.
In addition to that,
here
let's instead of logging loss.item,
let's actually uh log the
let's um do log 10,
I believe that's a function of the loss.
And I'll show you why in a second. Let's
optimize this.
Basically, I'd like to plot the log loss
instead of the loss because when you
plot the loss, many times it can have
this hockey stick appearance and log
squashes it in.
Uh so, it just kind of like looks nicer.
So, the x-axis is step I
and the y-axis will be the loss I.
And then here, this is 30.
Ideally, we wouldn't be hard coding
these.
Okay, so let's look at the loss.
Okay? It's again very thick because the
mini batch size is very small, but the
total loss over the training set is 2.3
and the the test or the dev set is 2.38
as well.
So so far so good. Uh let's try to now
decrease the learning rate
by a factor of 10
and train for another 50,000 iterations.
We'd hope that we would be able to beat
uh 2.32.
But again, we're just kind of like doing
this very haphazardly, so I don't
actually have confidence that our
learning rate is set very well, that our
learning rate decay, which we just do at
random, is set very well.
And um so the optimization here is kind
of suspect, to be honest, and this is
not how you would do it typically in
production. In production, you would
create parameters or hyper parameters
out of all these settings, and then you
would run lots of experiments and see
whichever ones are working well for you.
Okay.
So we have 2.17 now and 2.2. Okay. So
you see how the training and the
validation performance are starting to
slightly slowly depart.
So maybe we're getting the sense that
the neural net is getting good enough or
that number of parameters is large
enough that we are slowly starting to
overfit.
Uh let's maybe run one more iteration of
this
and see where we get.
But yeah, basically, you would be
running lots of experiments, and then
you are slowly scrutinizing whichever
ones give you the best dev performance.
And then once you find all the uh hyper
parameters that make your dev
performance good, you take that model
and you evaluate the test set
performance a single time. And that's
the number that you report in your paper
or wherever else you want to talk about
and brag about your model.
So, let's then rerun the plot and rerun
the train and dev.
And because we're getting lower loss
now, it is the case that the embedding
size of these was holding us back very
likely.
Okay, so 2.16 2.19 is what we're roughly
getting.
So, there's many ways to go from many
ways to go from here. We can continue
tuning the optimization.
We can continue, for example, playing
with the sizes of the neural net. Or we
can increase the number of um
words or characters, in our case, that
we are taking as an input. So, instead
of just three characters, we could be
taking more characters than as an input.
And that could further improve the loss.
Okay, so I changed the code slightly, so
we have here 200,000 steps of the
optimization. And in the first 100,000,
we're using a learning rate of 0.1. And
then in the next 100,000, we're using a
learning rate of 0.01.
This is the loss that I achieve.
And these are the performance on the
training and validation loss.
And in particular, the best validation
loss I've been able to obtain in the
last 30 minutes or so is 2.17.
So, now I invite you to beat this
number. And you have quite a few knobs
available to you to, I think, surpass
this number.
So, number one, you can of course change
the number of neurons in the hidden
layer of this model.
You can change the dimensionality of the
embedding uh lookup table.
You can change the number of characters
that are feeding in as an input um as
the context into this model.
And then, of course, you can change the
details of the optimization. How long
are we running? What is the learning
rate? How does it change over time?
Uh how does it decay?
Uh you can change the batch size, and
you may be able to actually achieve a
much better convergence speed in terms
of uh how many seconds or minutes it
takes to train the model and uh get uh
your result in terms of really good um
loss.
And then of course, I actually invite
you to read this paper. It is 19 pages,
but at this point you should actually be
able to read a good chunk of this paper
and understand
uh pretty good chunks of it.
And this paper also has quite a few
ideas for improvements that you can play
with.
So, all of those are knobs available to
you, and you should be able to beat this
number. I'm leaving that as an exercise
to the reader, and uh that's it for now,
and I'll see you next time.
Before we wrap up, I also wanted to show
how you would sample from the model.
So, we're going to generate 20 samples.
At first, we begin with all dots, so
that's the context. And then until we
generate the zeroth character again,
we're going to embed the current context
using the embedding table C.
Now, usually uh here, the first
dimension was the size of the training
set, but here we're only working with a
single example that we're generating, so
this is just um dimension one, just for
simplicity.
Um and so this embedding then gets
projected into the hidden state. You get
the logits. Now, we calculate the
probabilities. For that, you can use
f.softmax
um of logits, and that just basically
exponentiates the logits and makes them
sum to one.
And similar to cross entropy, it is
careful that there's no overflows.
Once we have the probabilities, we
sample from them using torch.multinomial
to get our next index, and then we shift
the context window to append the index
and record it.
And then we can just um decode all the
integers to strings and print them out.
And so these are some example samples,
and you can see that the model now works
much better. So, the words here are much
more word-like or name-like. So, we have
things like ham, um
joes,
uh lela,
you know, it's starting to sound a
little bit more name-like. So, we're
definitely making progress, uh, but we
can still improve on this model quite a
lot.
Okay, sorry. There's some bonus content.
I wanted to mention that I want to make
these notebooks more accessible. And so,
I don't want you to have to, like,
install Jupyter notebooks and torch and
everything else. So, I will be sharing a
link to a Google Colab.
And the Google Colab will look like a
notebook in your browser. And you can
just go to a URL, and you'll be able to
execute all the code that you saw in the
Google Colab. And so, this is me
executing the code in this lecture, and
I shortened it a little bit.
Uh, but basically, you you're able to
train the exact same network, and then
plot and sample from the model, and
everything is ready for you to, like,
tinker with the numbers right there in
your browser. No installation necessary.
Um, so, I just wanted to point that out,
and the link to this will be in the
video description.